In the last video, we extracted only the bicep for faster simulation tests, and then we explored the effects of the muscle parameters in the set muscle activation parameter node.
지난 영상에서는 빠른 시뮬레…션을 위해 이두근만 추출했고, `Set Muscle Activation Parameter` 노드에서 근육 파라미터를 설정했습니다.
Now let's go ahead and start setting up our fat layer and start running our fat layer simulation.
이제 지방(fat) 레이어를 세팅하고 지방 레이어 시뮬레이션을 실행해 봅시다.
Let's find our static mesh fat layer first.
먼저 정적 메시(static mesh) 형태의 지방 레이어를 찾아봅시다.
If you look at this, this contains over a million vertices.
보시면 정점(vertex)이 백만 개가 넘습니다.
That's really a high count of vertices.
정점 수가 정말 많죠.
So let's go ahead and start down sampling it first.
그래서 우선 다운샘플링부터 하겠습니다.
And do that by duplicated.
복제본을 만들어서 진행할게요.
And I'm going to rename this as a low res version.
그리고 이걸 저해상도(low‑res) 버전으로 이름을 바꾸겠습니다.
Make sure to save this.
저장해 주세요.
And then now we can leave this in the environment by dragging it out.
이제 이걸 드래그해서 레벨(환경)에 배치해 둡니다.
Press F to zoom in.
F 키를 눌러 확대합니다.
Now over here, we can go into the modeling mode.
여기서 모델링( Modeling ) 모드로 들어갑니다.
This will open up a menu of tools, and we want to go to mesh, then simplify.
도구 메뉴가 열리면 Mesh → Simplify로 이동합니다.
For the options, for the simplifier type, let's go ahead and select existing positions and target mode.
옵션에서 Simpli…fy에 대해 Existing Positions와 Target Mode를 선택하겠습니다.
Let's select vertex count because we have an ideal vertex count in mind, which is to 20,000 vertex count.
Vertex Count를 선택하겠습니다. 왜냐하면 목표 정점 수를 정해 두었는데 약 20,000개이기 때문입니다.
And make sure you select discard attributes, otherwise it wouldn't work on this example.
그리고 ‘Discard Attributes’를 꼭 체크하세요. 그렇지 않으면 이 예제에서는 동작하지 않습니다.
And now you can see the resolution became much more coarse.
이제 해상도가 훨씬 거칠어졌다는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
And that's exactly what I want.
바로 이게 우리가 원했던 상태입니다.
Make sure you hit accept.
‘Accept’를 눌러 확정하세요.
Now there it is.
이렇게 됐네요.
We have our low res version of the fat layer.
지방 레이어의 저해상도 버전을 얻었습니다.
Make sure you save this.
저장해 주세요.
And now, let's go ahead and create a tetrahedral mesh for the fat layer only.
이제 지방 레이어에 대해서만 테트(사면체) 메쉬를 생성하겠습니다.
You can do that by creating another flesh acid.
Flesh 애셋을 하나 더 만들어서 그렇게 할 수 있습니다.
And similar to the tet mesh muscle one, let's call this tet mesh fat flesh acid.
근육용 테트 메쉬 애셋과 유사하게, 이번 것은 ‘Tet Mesh Fat’용 Flesh 애셋으로 만들겠습니다.
Create a new data flow graph.
새 데이터 플로 그래프(Data Flow Graph)를 만듭니다.
Make sure you save.
저장하세요.
And now we have a brand new flesh acid.
이제 새 Flesh 애셋이 준비됐습니다.
Before I do anything, let's make sure I create a new folder called tet mesh.
먼저 ‘TetMesh’라는 새 폴더를 하나 만들어 둡니다.
Now let's make sure we drag the tet mesh versions of things in here so that we don't touch it anymore.
이제 원본/고해상도 버전 같은 것들을 여기에 옮겨 넣어서 더 이상 건드리지 않도록 하겠습니다.
We want to avoid accidental revaluation of the graph.
그래프를 실수로 다시 평가(Evaluate)하는 일을 피하고 싶기 때문입니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
Now let's go to the tet mesh and start bringing in the fat layer.
이제 테트 메쉬 그래프로 가서 지방 레이어를 불러오겠습니다.
You can do that by calling static mesh.
이를 위해 ‘Static Mesh’ 노드를 추가합니다.
And here is our low res version of the fat layer.
여기가 지방 레이어의 저해상도 버전입니다.
Let's convert this to a collection by calling static mesh to collection.
‘Static Mesh to Collection’ 노드로 컬렉션으로 변환합니다.
Now you can see there is our converted fat layer.
변환된 지방 레이어가 보이죠.
You can also view the vertices here.
여기에서 정점들도 확인할 수 있습니다.
You can see it has exactly 20,000 vertices.
정확히 20,000개의 정점을 가진 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
This is our downsampled version.
이게 다운샘플된 버전입니다.
And after that, let's make a tetrahedral mesh from this by calling create tetrahedron node.
이제 ‘Create Tetrahedron’ 노드로부터 사면체 메쉬를 생성하겠습니다.
In this case, let's go to tet wild.
이번에는 TetWild를 사용하겠습니다.
Set next generation to 20.
Next Generation(세대 수)을 20으로 설정합니다.
And in this case, we do want the fat layer or the tet mesh of the fat layer to be very close to the input surface.
그리고 이번에는 지방 레이어의 테트 메쉬가 입력 표면과 매우 가깝게 맞도록 하고 싶습니다.
In that case, we want this epsilon value to be low.
그럴 때는 이 epsilon 값을 낮게 설정해야 합니다.
So let's add a one zero to make it much lower.
그래서 숫자 하나(0)를 더 붙여 훨씬 낮춰 줍니다.
And then make sure you check the corset box.
그리고 ‘corset’ 체크박스를 체크해 주세요.
Now we can start evaluating this node.
이제 이 노드를 Evaluate(평가)할 수 있습니다.
It's going to take a while.
이 작업은 시간이 조금 걸립니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
Now we just got back from our node evaluation.
노드 평가가 방금 끝났습니다.
The whole process took about 10 minutes.
전체 과정에 약 10분이 걸렸습니다.
Let's go ahead and create a flesh asset terminal to save this into a flesh asset.
이 결과를 Flesh 애셋으로 저장하기 위해 ‘Flesh Asset Terminal’을 추가합시다.
Now make sure you save the flesh asset or the deal flow graph.
Flesh 애셋과 데이터 플로 그래프를 저장해 주세요.
Now let's go back to our muscle setup.
이제 근육 세팅으로 돌아갑니다.
And let's import the fat layer tetrahedral mesh.
그리고 지방 레이어의 테트라 메쉬를 가져옵니다.
We've done this before.
이건 이전에 해봤죠.
Let's go ahead and create a get flesh asset node.
‘Get Flesh Asset’ 노드를 추가합니다.
And then import our fat tetrahedral mesh here.
여기에 지방 테트라 메쉬를 로드합니다.
There is our fat layer tetrahedral mesh.
지방 레이어의 테트라 메쉬가 준비됐습니다.
For the sake of the tutorial, let's group the set of the flow nodes from the last tutorial.
튜토리얼 진행을 위해 지난 시간에 만든 노드들을 하나로 그룹화하겠습니다.
And if we select that, we can type C to bring out a comment box.
그룹을 선택한 상태에서 C 키를 눌러 코멘트 박스를 띄울 수 있습니다.
And let's call this muscle simulation test.
이 그룹은 ‘Muscle Simulation Test’라고 이름 붙이겠습니다.
Once we have them grouped, we can drag them around.
그룹화하면 블록 단위로 쉽게 이동할 수 있습니다.
And let's go ahead and connect this back to the terminal so that we can bypass the simulation test nodes that we created last time.
그리고 지난번에 만들었던 시뮬레이션 테스트 노드들을 우회(bypass)할 수 있도록 연결을 정리하겠습니다.
Now at this point, since we just have the fat layer here, let's assign some mass and stiffness.
이제 현재는 지방 레이어만 있으니, 질량(mass)과 강성(stiffness) 값을 설정해 줍니다.
Let's call get fleshDefaultProperties.
‘Get FleshDefaultProperties’를 사용합니다.
For this example, let's set density to be 100 and vertex stiffness to be 10,000.
이번 예제에서는 밀도(density)를 100, 정점 강성(vertex stiffness)을 10,000으로 설정하겠습니다.
We want the density and the stiffness to be lower than the muscles because we want the muscles to mainly drive the fat layer instead of the other way around.
지방 레이어가 다른 것에 끌려가기보다 밀도와 강성 값이 지방 레이어를 주로 지배하도록 하고 싶습니다.
And eventually, the muscle deformation will propagate to the fat layer.
결국 근육 변형이 지방 레이어로 전달될 것입니다.
Once we have that, let's combine the muscles over here and also the fat here.
이 값들을 설정했으면 여기의 근육들과 여기의 지방을 합칩니다.
We call an append-hedral collection node.
‘Append Tetrahedral Collection’ 노드를 사용합니다.
Now let's connect the collection over here.
이제 컬렉션을 여기로 연결합니다.
Now you can see everything is combined.
모든 것이 합쳐진 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Now at this point, we need to bind some spring constraints.
이제 스프링 제약을 바인딩해야 합니다.
So we've done that before.
이것도 전에 해봤죠.
It's called set vertex triangle position target binding.
이름은 ‘Set Vertex Triangle Position Target Binding’입니다.
However, in this case, we want to select a group of vertices to bind to the muscles.
하지만 이번에는 근육에 바인딩할 정점 그룹만 선택하려고 합니다.
So we only want the inner surface of the fat layer.
즉, 지방 레이어의 ‘안쪽 표면’만 원합니다.
So remember, the fat layer is a thin layer.
기억하세요, 지방 레이어는 얇은 층입니다.
It's a closed surface.
닫힌 표면이죠.
So we only want the inside vertices to bind to the muscles.
그래서 안쪽 정점들만 근육에 바인딩하겠습니다.
So we can do that by constructing a vertex selection.
이를 위해 정점 선택(Selection)을 구성하겠습니다.
Let's go ahead and start painting on the fat layer.
그럼 지방 레이어 위에서 페인팅을 시작하겠습니다.
And then transfer it to the inner side of the fat layer tetrapetal mesh.
그 후 이 선택을 지방 레이어의 테트라 메쉬 안쪽으로 전달(Transfer)합니다.
The thing we want to do is bring in the set mesh against the low-res fat layer and convert it to a collection.
해야 할 일은 저해상도 지방 레이어에 브러…시로 칠한 선택을 가져와 컬렉션으로 변환하는 것입니다.
And now at this point, we can start painting on it.
이제 여기서 실제로 페인팅을 시작할 수 있습니다.
So as you can see, we have the fat layer here.
보시다시피 여기 지방 레이어가 있습니다.
Let's use the brush tool.
브러시 도구를 사용합시다.
Set the strength to one.
강도를 1로 설정합니다.
And make sure we have the visibility filter because we...
그리고 가시성 필터(Visibility Filter)를 사용하도록 설정하세요. 왜냐하면…
The idea is we want to paint on the outer surface and then invert it so that we have the inner surface.
개념은 바깥쪽 표면에 먼저 칠한 다음 그것을 반전(invert)해서 안쪽 표면 선택을 얻는 것입니다.
So let's go ahead and paint on the outer surface.
그럼 외부 표면부터 칠해봅시다.
All right.
좋습니다.
We just took a few minutes to paint this outer surface of the fat layer.
지방 레이어의 바깥 표면을 몇 분 동안 칠했습니다.
And now after that, we can invert the current surface so that it now...
이제 현재 표면 선택을 반전시키면…
We inverted the selection.
선택을 반전했습니다.
Then now we have a selection of the internal surface.
그러면 내부 표면이 선택됩니다.
That's good.
좋습니다.
Make sure we save this.
이 상태를 저장하세요.